Advertising & Public Relations

COLLEGE: Journalism & Mass Communications

MAJOR: Advertising & Public Relations

DEGREE OFFERED: Bachelor of Journalism

HOURS REQUIRED: 120

MINIMUM CUMULATIVE GPA: 2.0 for graduation

MINOR AVAILABLE: No

ADVISOR: Andrea Spader

DESCRIPTION

Professors: Brown, Hachtmann, Mitchell, Shipley (emeritus)

Associate Professor: Struthers

Assistant Professors: Jones, Kiambi, Wagler, Wang, Yan

Professors of Practice: Goff, James (emeritus), Larsen

Assistant Professors of Practice: Sallee, Tidball

The advertising and public relations major prepares students for careers in a wide variety of communication-related areas. Recent graduates have taken jobs in more than 20 states and several other countries in diverse careers such as retail and corporate advertising and marketing, media sales, brand management, media planning, account management, research, public relations, media relations, special event planning, mobile and digital communications, creative concepting, sports media relations, digital insights and analytics, copywriting and layout and design.

The advertising and public relations faculty believes that a successful career must be built upon a solid foundation, an education that combines theory and practice. To achieve that end, the major offers courses in copywriting, layout, media planning, graphics, campaign development, research, management, coding, and strategic communications. The curriculum is designed to emphasize strategy, planning and implementation in creative problem-solving.

Much emphasis is placed on individual relationships between faculty and students, an interaction vital to a student’s creative development. An advisor also helps each student tailor an academic plan to meet his or her interests and needs.

In advertising and public relations classes, students often work with actual clients who present real-life problems. This experience gives students a professional perspective on problem solving in many sectors including nonprofit, retail, small business and community organizations as well as large corporations. Students are encouraged to augment their academic experience with internships.

The faculty, with many professional contacts both locally and nationwide, actively help students find jobs within the state and throughout the country. Students interested in majoring in advertising and public relations should contact the college office in 147 Andersen Hall, 402-472-3041.

MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Specific Major Requirements

The major is 40 hours in advertising and public relations.

The courses required for a major in advertising and public relations are as follows:

ADPR 151, ADPR 221, ADPR 283, JOMC 100, JOMC 101, JOMC 130, JOMC 131, JOMC 132, JOMC 133, JOMC 134, JOMC 486, and JOMC 487.

Additionally, all ADPR majors take one of the following three capstone courses: ADPR 429, ADPR 439, or ADPR 489, as well as 12 hours from approved electives for the major.

The 12 elective hours may comprise one of five optional areas of emphasis, including account services, creative/interactive, digital communication, public relations or sports communication. Students also may select the elective courses from multiple areas of emphasis to provide a broad background. Among the 12 elective hours, students may select courses from ADPR, BRDC, JOMC or JOUR. At least 9 of the 12 elective hours must be chosen from ADPR elective options numbered 300 or higher. However, for the public relations emphasis JOUR 201, JOUR 202 and ADPR 207 can apply.

The account services emphasis includes the following: ADPR 329, ADPR 339, ADPR 360, ADPR 434, ADPR 481, and ADPR 484.

The creative/interactive emphasis includes the following: ADPR 323, ADPR 329, ADPR 333, ADPR 339, ADPR 433, ADPR 447, ADPR 458, ADPR 459, ADPR 483, and ADPR 484.

The digital communication emphasis includes the following: ADPR 329, ADPR 339, ADPR 360, ADPR 434, ADPR 458, ADPR 459, ADPR 466; JOUR 304 and JOUR 407.

The public relations emphasis includes the following: ADPR 207, ADPR 329, ADPR 339, ADPR 417, ADPR 437, ADPR 450, ADPR 451, ADPR 457, ADPR 466; JOUR 201 and JOUR 202.

The sports communication emphasis includes the following: JOMC 150 and at least 3 more hours from Section A (ADPR 464, BRDC 375, JOUR 326 or a sports internship in ADPR, BRDC or JOUR). The remaining 6 hours may be selected from either Section A or Section B (ADPR 151, ADPR 207, ADPR 283, ADPR 450, ADPR 451, JOUR 201 or JOUR 202). NOTE: The 12 hours for the emphasis may not include any course already required for the major.

If approved by the associate dean, all areas of emphasis may further include the following: ADPR X91, BRDC X91, JOUR X91, JOMC X91, ADPR 495, ADPR 496 and ADPR 499H.

Students may complete two majors in the College of Journalism and Mass Communications by completing all requirements for each major. However, the second major in the college will not take the place of a concentration or any of the 72 hours required outside the college.

Graduating seniors also must complete JOMC 98 Senior Assessment. Typically, JOMC 98 (0 credit) is taken in the last semester. However, seniors who have completed all courses for the major may take it in the term preceding graduation.

ADDITIONAL MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Internship Policy

Students may be able to earn credit for internships under certain circumstances. Please go to the college website and find the Internship Policy under the Student Services tab.

Credit in Special Experiences

Students may earn up to 6 credit hours toward the degree in some student experiences: Jacht, National Student Advertising Competition, photojournalism reports, depth reports and others. Students may repeat the same course again for additional credit hours, but those credits will not count toward the degree inside or outside the major. Talk with an academic advisor for further information or specific questions.

Art

COLLEGE: Fine & Performing Arts

MAJOR: Art

DEGREE OFFERED: Bachelor of Arts, Bachelor of Fine Arts

HOURS REQUIRED: 120

MINIMUM CUMULATIVE GPA: 2.0 for graduation

MINOR AVAILABLE: Yes

ADVISOR: Christy Aggens

DESCRIPTION

Director: Robert Derr, 120 Richards Hall

Professors: Derr, Fritz, Kunc, Pinnell, Souto

Associate Professors: Bohls, Cal, Dominguez, Holz, Ingraham, Williams

Assistant Professors: Asher, Pickering, Sontheimer, Sutherlen

Assistant Professors of Practice: Cole, Syron

The School of Art, Art History and Design offers students the opportunity to investigate visual art through a variety of experiences. The art major enables students to attain proficiency in the practice of art and knowledge of the history of art as part of a general college education. Some may want to devote themselves to a period of intensive studio art education, while others may be interested in pursuing art for the purpose of building cultural awareness and critical thinking skills. Two undergraduate degrees are available to art majors. The student's career goals will determine the appropriate option.

The bachelor of arts degree (BA) is a liberal arts degree with about forty-five percent of the course work in the School of Art, Art History and Design, providing the flexibility to study various academic disciplines outside of art. The bachelor of fine arts degree (BFA) is a professional degree, the usual preparation for professional careers or graduate study in studio art, and includes about seventy percent of the course work from the School of Art, Art History and Design. Increased studio art requirements in the BFA allow for specialization within a chosen area or a customized studio experience.

Bachelor of Arts Degree at a Glance

ACE Requirements 30

Languages: Classical & Modern 0-6

Select from the list of “Approved Courses” found under “College Degree Requirements.”

Art Major Requirements 54

Minors 18-24

Electives 6-18

Total Hours Required for Graduation 120

Bachelor of Fine Arts Degree at a Glance

ACE Requirements 30

Art Major Requirements 84

Electives 6

Total Hours Required for Graduation 120

MAJOR DEPARTMENT ADMISSION

Any student who meets college admission requirements may declare a major in art.

MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Bachelor of Arts Requirements

BA Requirements 54

Required Foundation 15

ARTP 150 Studio Foundation 3

ARTP 151 Color and Composition 3

ARTP 152 Three-Dimensional Design 3

DRAW 201 Drawing 3

DRAW 202 Life Drawing 3

ARTP 400 Capstone Art Experience 3

Studio Electives 18

Studio Thesis Hours 3

Art History 15

AHIS 101 Cave Paintings to Cathedrals 3

AHIS 102 Renaissance to Modern Art 3

Art History electives (including a minimum of 3 credits in courses numbered above 299) 9

Studio Area Option

Studio elective hours may be used to pursue an optional 12-credit focus in one studio area, which includes a minimum of 3 credits of Studio Thesis (499). Available areas are ceramics, drawing, painting, photography, printmaking, and sculpture.

Minor Requirements

BA students are required to complete a minimum of one minor. A second major can be used to satisfy the minor requirement.

Bachelor of Fine Arts Requirements

BFA Requirements 84

Required Foundation 15

ARTP 150 Studio Foundation 3

ARTP 151 Color and Composition 3

ARTP 152 Three-Dimensional Design 3

DRAW 201 Drawing 3

DRAW 202 Life Drawing 3

Required Distribution 15

CERM 231 Beginning Ceramics: Wheelthrowing or CERM 232 Beginning Ceramics: Handbuilding 3

PANT 251 Beginning Painting I 3

PHOT 261 Beginning Photography-Digital 3

PRNT 241 Beginning Printmaking I 3

SCLP 211 Beginning Sculpture I 3

ARTP 400 Capstone Art Experience 3

Studio Area Option 18

Studio Electives 18

Art History 15

AHIS 101 Cave Paintings to Cathedrals 3

AHIS 102 Renaissance to Modern Art 3

Art History electives (including a minimum of 3 credits in courses numbered above 299) 9

Studio Area Option Requirement

BFA students must designate an option area and complete 18 credits in the chosen area, including a minimum of 3 credits of Studio Thesis (499). Available areas include ceramics, drawing, painting, photography, printmaking, sculpture, and interdisciplinary studies. Students with an interdisciplinary emphasis will work with their advisor to identify the 18 credits that will be used for option requirements.

ADDITIONAL MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

BA Degree

Grade Rules

C- and D Grades

Minimum grade for all major requirements is C.

Pass/No Pass Limits

All courses taken for major requirements must be for letter grade, unless the course is only offered Pass/No Pass.

Course Level Requirement

A minimum of 3 credits of studio art and 3 credits of art history must be taken in courses numbered above 299.

Extended Education, Independent Study Rules, Internship Credit Rules, Transfer Credit Rules

No more than 6 hours of independent study courses may count toward the major in the BA degree. This includes all courses numbered 390, 392, 395, 396, 490, 492, 495, 496, and 499H offered by the School of Art, Art History and Design.
At least 12 credit hours in studio art and 9 credit hours in art history of the required BA courses must be taken at UNL. Courses taken at other academic institutions may be substituted for the remaining required courses subject to evaluation by the department.

Time and Credit Guidelines

The School of Art, Art History and Design adheres to the following time and credit guidelines established by the National Association of Schools of Art and Design (NASAD):

In studio courses, one hour of credit represents three hours of work each week of the 16-week semester. Two of the hours are spent in class with the instructor, and one hour of additional work is expected outside of regularly scheduled class time.
In lecture/discussion courses, one hour of credit represents one hour each week in class, and two hours each week of work outside of class for the duration of the 16-week semester.

BFA Degree

Grade Rules

C- and D Grades

Minimum grade for all major requirements is C.

Pass/No Pass Limits

All courses taken for major requirements must be for letter grade, unless the course is only offered Pass/No Pass.

Course Level Requirement

A minimum of 3 credits of art history must be taken in courses numbered above 299.

Extended Education, Independent Study Rules, Internship Credit Rules, Transfer Credit Rules

No more than 9 hours of independent study courses may count toward the major in the BA degree. This includes all courses numbered 390, 392, 395, 396, 490, 492, 495, 496, and 499H offered by the School of Art, Art History and Design.
At least 36 credit hours in studio art and 9 credit hours in art history of the required BFA courses must be taken at UNL. Courses taken at other academic institutions may be substituted for the remaining required courses subject to evaluation by the department.

Time and Credit Guidelines

The School of Art, Art History and Design adheres to the following time and credit guidelines established by the National Association of Schools of Art and Design (NASAD):

In studio courses, 1 hour of credit represents three hours of work each week of the 16-week semester. Two of the hours are spent in class with the instructor, and one hour of additional work is expected outside of regularly scheduled class time.
In lecture/discussion courses, 1 hour of credit represents one hour each week in class, and two hours each week of work outside of class for the duration of the 16-week semester.

REQUIREMENTS FOR MINOR OFFERED BY DEPARTMENT

Plan A Minor in Art – 18 credits

Art History: AHIS 101 or AHIS 102 3

Studio Electives 12

Select from the following areas: ceramics, drawing, painting, photography, printmaking, sculpture, special topics, Art at Cedar Point

Additional Elective 3

Any art history or studio art course

A grade of C or better is required in all courses. Classes taken Pass/No Pass will not be applicable toward the minor.
A maximum of 6 transfer credits will apply toward minor requirements.

Note: Graphic Design majors must complete an additional 12 credits of studio electives beyond what is required for the major if this minor is chosen.

CEHS International Minor

COLLEGE: Education & Human Sciences

MAJOR: CEHS International Minor

DEGREE OFFERED: Minor only

HOURS REQUIRED: 18

MINIMUM CUMULATIVE GPA:

MINOR AVAILABLE: Yes

ADVISOR: AnnMarie Gottner

DESCRIPTION

The College of Education and Human Sciences offers a minor in International Studies, open to all undergraduate students.

REQUIREMENTS FOR MINOR OFFERED BY DEPARTMENT

Minor–Plan A Requirements – 18 hours

Learning Outcomes

In fulfilling the requirements of the CEHS International Studies Minor, students will achieve the following three learning outcomes.

Outcome 1: Human Ecosystem - Students will be able to articulate the culturally specific ways in which children/youth, families, schools, and communities are viewed and services to them are provided.

Outcome 2: Global Self-Awareness - Students will be able to address significant issues in the world and the relationship of these issues to individual decision-making.

Outcome 3: International Dimensions - Students will understand and be able to articulate how the discipline of their major (or one of their majors) is viewed and practiced in another culture.

9 of 18 credit hours must be from courses with the CEHS prefix or a prefix representing a CEHS department.

Students must take at least 6 credts from the list of courses approved to meet Outcomes 1 and Outcomes 2, students must take at least 1 credit to meet Outcome 3.

Additional courses: In addition to the 7 minimum credits required to meet Outcomes 1, 2, and 3; to complete the overall 18 credits required; students may select from:

Any course approved to meet the CEHS International Studies Minor.
Any course approved to meet the Global Studies major in the College of Arts and Sciences.

Additional courses: In addition to the 7 minimum credits required to meet Outcomes 1, 2, and 3; to complete the overall 18-credits required; students may select from:

Coaching Minor

COLLEGE: Education & Human Sciences

MAJOR: Coaching Minor

DEGREE OFFERED: Minor only

HOURS REQUIRED: 15

MINIMUM CUMULATIVE GPA: 2.5

MINOR AVAILABLE: Yes

ADVISOR:

DESCRIPTION

This minor is only available to those students who have a non-teaching major in the College of Education and Human Sciences. Teacher education candidates can complete the coaching endorsement program which is a supplemental endorsement for students in teacher education.

Contact: Dr. Tom Wandzilak, twandzilak1@unl.edu, 402-472-8626

REQUIREMENTS FOR MINOR OFFERED BY DEPARTMENT

Course Requirements

ATHC 235 (3 hrs)

ATHC 279 (3 hrs)

ATHC 494 (3 hrs)

Select three from the following: ATHC 311, ATHC 312, ATHC 317, ATHC 318 (6 hrs)

OTHER

Criminal History Background Check Requirement

The College of Education and Human Sciences (CEHS) has the responsibility to ensure that all students who interact with children of all ages, served by schools or other public or private agencies meet a high level of personal, professional and ethical behavior. These CEHS students must complete an official criminal history background check through the CEHS vendor, prior to participating in a field experience or internship. Students are responsible for the cost of any required criminal history background check and will be required to complete one upon admission to a program and/or an initial field placement. Eighteen months after the initial background check has been completed, undergraduate students are required to complete the CEHS self-disclosure report, a self-report collected by the college. Graduate students will be required to complete the self-disclosure report at the same time as the initial background check is conducted and again eighteen months later. If more than three years have elapsed after the initial background check is conduced, CEHS students must complete an additional background check prior to participating in a field experience or internship. Students are responsible for the cost of additional background checks.

Students with felony or any misdemeanor charges or convictions, as reported on the background check, may be contacted by the College. Depending upon the frequency and severity of the charges and/or convictions, students may be required to meet with the Director of Professional Experiences. If any new charges or convictions are acquired after a background check has been completed, students are required to report those to the Director of Professional Experiences within two weeks after the event occurs. Failure to disclose any new information concerning one's criminal history can lead to removal from the program. Continued participation in school or community field experiences in the College will be based on the type and number of convictions, the recency of those occurrences, and whether they violate the requirements of the Nebraska Department of Education and/or the Nebraska Department of Health and Human Services. If the convictions are deemed to be serious in nature, a student may be prohibited from participating in a field experience in a pre-school, school or public agency setting. The student may then be referred to the department chair for further disciplinary action.

Professional and Ethical Behavior: Avoiding Risky Behaviors

Students planning to enter professions in education or the human sciences must be able to demonstrate that they are individuals of strong moral character who can make mature decisions for themselves and others. Therefore, the College of Education and Human Sciences requires that its students show a high degree of moral character and the ability to act in a responsible manner. Students must consider how the College, the profession, an employer, or the community perceive or evaluate the impact of any questionable behavior. Students' success in their profession is impaired by taking risks that are unacceptable for children, demonstrating a lack of professionalism and good judgment, and showing disregard for one's personal reputation or the integrity of the College.

The College of Education and Human Sciences reserves the right to evaluate student fitness for the profession and deny entry to or dismiss a student from any program if, through the reasonable exercise of the judgment of its Certification Officer or the Director of Professional Experiences, the College determines that the student's behavior represents a lack of integrity, questionable moral/ethical character, or represents risk to young persons. Such behaviors shall be adequate foundation to deny the student's participation in any practicum or field experience to protect the interests and safety of children. The consequences of unprofessional, unethical or risky behavior will depend upon the unique circumstances involved.

Appeal to the Dean

Should a student object to the determination made by the Certification Officer or the Director of Professional Experiences with respect to a criminal behavior or unprofessional behavior, the student may appeal to the Dean of the College, in writing, within ten days of the determination, requesting the Dean of the College to investigate and review the determination. The student's written appeal shall clearly explain the basis for the appeal. The Dean will review the student's basis for appeal and is authorized but not required to look into related concerns, whether or not sure concerns are contained in the student's written appeal. The Dean shall render a decision on the appeal as soon as reasonably possible, but in no case longer than 20 days following the initiation of the appeal. Once the Dean has completed the review and investigation, he or she shall deliver to the student and the Certification Officer or the Director of Professional Experiences a written decision, which shall be final and not subject to further appeal or review with the University of Nebraska.

Communication Studies

COLLEGE: Arts & Sciences

MAJOR: Communication Studies

DEGREE OFFERED: Bachelor of Arts or Bachelor of Science

HOURS REQUIRED: 120

MINIMUM CUMULATIVE GPA: 2.0 for graduation

MINOR AVAILABLE: Yes

ADVISOR: Kathy Castle

DESCRIPTION

Chair: Dawn O. Braithwaite, 433 Oldfather

Director of Speech & Debate: Aaron Duncan

Professors: Braithwaite, Kellas, Krone, R. Lee, Seiler

Associate Professors: Soliz

Assistant Professors: Palmer-Wackerly

Assistant Professors of Practice: Castle, Duncan

Communication studies is a social science and humanistic field of study, research, and application. The mission of the Department of Communication Studies is to examine human symbolic activity as it shapes and is shaped by relationships, institutions, and societies. This work concerns how, why, and with what effects people communicate through verbal and nonverbal messages. Through research, teaching, and service, the Department devotes particular attention to understanding the ways in which communication erodes and sustains collaboration within and among local, national, and global communities.

Communication competencies are among those most highly desired in professional, personal, organizational, and civic arenas. Additionally, a major in Communication Studies goes beyond learning communication skills by fostering a world view that demonstrates a commitment to communication, collaboration, and community. Communication Studies majors go on to careers in sales, marketing, human resources, customer service, nonprofit management, event planning, fund raising, public relations, management, and government, to name just a few. Majors also go on to graduate school and law school.

University Speech & Debate

The University of Nebraska–Lincoln offers a nationally recognized speech and debate program of participation in campus and intercollegiate debate, public speaking, and interpretation events. The program gives students the opportunity to compete at the local, state, regional, and national level. No previous debate or speech experience is required. All students who are in good standing may take part in intercollegiate debate and forensics.

Graduate Work. Graduate programs leading to the master of arts and doctor of philosophy degrees are offered in the department. A detailed description of these programs appears in the Graduate Studies Bulletin.

MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Specific Major Requirements

All prospective majors must consult and register with a departmental advisor. Majors are expected to meet regularly with their advisor. An approved program of study must be filed at the time students declare the major or within the first 12 hours of course work in the major. In order to graduate with a communication studies major, students must have an approved program of study. The minimum number of hours for a major in communication studies is 36. The 36-hour requirement must include the following:

1. Complete both COMM 101 and either COMM 201 or 202. These courses should be completed within the first twelve hours in communication studies of a student’s program.

2. Complete one of the following: COMM 109, COMM 205, COMM 209, COMM 212, COMM 220, COMM 286, or COMM 295.

3. Complete two of the following: COMM 250, COMM 271 or COMM 283.

4. Complete a minimum of 21 hours of communication studies courses at or above the 300 level.

5. Of the 21 hours, at least 9 must be at the 400 level including COMM495, with no more than 3 of those hours coming from either 390 or 397.

6. No more than 3 hours of internship, independent study or assistantship may count toward the 36-hour requirement in the major.

Program Assessment. In order to assist the department in evaluating the effectiveness of its programs, majors will be required to complete an assessment of the major. This assessment will be implemented in the communication studies capstone course: COMM 495.

Results of participation in this assessment activity will in no way affect a student’s GPA, but could prevent or delay graduation if the assessment is not completed as required.

Minor Requirements

A communication studies major must have either an approved Plan A minor or two approved Plan B minors. A departmental advisor must approve the minor.

ADDITIONAL MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Prerequisite Requirements/Rules

COMM 101 must be completed before a student can enroll in any 400-level course.

COMM 101, COMM 201 or COMM 202 must be taken before COMM 495.

Grade Rules

C- and D Grades

A grade of C or above is required for all courses in the major.

Pass/No Pass Limits

No course taken Pass/No Pass will be counted toward the major or the minor, with the exception of 3 hours of either COMM 297 or COMM 397.

REQUIREMENTS FOR MINOR OFFERED BY DEPARTMENT

Plan A

This minor consists of a minimum of 18 hours in communication studies courses with at least 9 hours at or above the 300 level. The 18-hour requirement must include the following:

1. COMM 101

2. Complete one of the following: COMM 109, COMM 205, COMM 209, COMM 212, COMM 220, COMM 286, or COMM 295.

3. A minimum of 9 hours must be taken in communication studies classes at or above the 300 level excluding COMM 297 and COMM 395.

4. Of the 9 hours, at least 3 must be at the 400 level. COMM 101 must be completed before a student can enroll in any 400-level course. COMM 395 cannot be used to meet this requirement.

5. The department encourages qualified students to enroll in internship, independent study, and education abroad experiences in order to supplement classroom experiences. However, none of these is a substitute for classroom experiences. No more than 3 hours of internship, independent study, or education abroad credits may count toward the 18-credit-hour requirement in the minor.

Plan B

12 hours of communication studies courses with at least 9 hours at or above the 200 level, excluding COMM 297 or COMM 395. A maximum of 3 hours of internship or independent study may apply to the 12-hour requirement.

Computer Engineering (Omaha)

COLLEGE: Engineering

MAJOR: Computer Engineering (Omaha)

DEGREE OFFERED: Bachelor of Science in Computer Engineering

HOURS REQUIRED: 124

MINIMUM CUMULATIVE GPA: 2.5 for graduation

MINOR AVAILABLE: No

ADVISOR: Roger Sash

DESCRIPTION

Chair: Jerry Hudgins, PKI 206C

Professors: Alexander, Asgarpoor, Balkir, Boye, Chen, Choobineh, Hoffman, Hudgins, Ianno, Lu, Nguyen, Otu, Perez, Qian, Sayood, Schubert, Sharif, Sutter, Woollam, Wysocki

Professor of Practice: Bauer

Associate Professors: Ci, Franke-Schubert, Han, Hui, Jang, Peng, Qiao, Sash, Snyder, Vakilzadian, Varner, Yang

Associate Professors of Practice: Detloff, Gilmore

Assistant Professors: Argyropoulos, Harms, Qu

Assistant Professor of Practice: McCreight

Phone: 402-554-2288

FAX: 402-554-2289

Website: engineering.unl.edu/ece

Email: rsash1@unl.edu

The computer engineering program is administered by the Department of Electrical and Computer Engineering and the bachelor of science degree program is accredited by the Engineering Accreditation Commission of ABET, http://www.abet.org.

Mission

The mission of the Department of Electrical and Computer Engineering (ECE) programs on the Omaha Campus at the University of Nebraska is to develop and maintain programs of excellence in teaching and research which meet the educational needs of its constituents, which will support the state of Nebraska in its development as a leading center for high-technology computer/electronics/telecommunications industry and which will support national needs for well-educated ECE professionals.

Program Educational Objectives

The Program Educational Objectives (PEOs) for the computer engineering program are a statement of what its graduates are doing or are capable of doing three to five years after graduation. The students in the computer engineering program receive a strong foundation in engineering science and design that not only enables them to pursue productive careers in the computer engineering field but also in other areas such as business, management, and medicine. Typical industries in which computer engineering graduates are employed include microprocessor/embedded system design, digital design, hardware/software integration, and computer architecture and parallel processing.

The Program Educational Objectives for the computer engineering program are that graduates will be:

1. Employed in business, academia, or government.

2. Successful engineers who have established productive careers in their field and have contributed to improve and provide innovative and effective solutions in computer engineering or related fields.

3. Demonstrating technical and decision-making processes and the human interactions necessary to produce viable, responsible, and sustainable technological solutions.

4. Engaging in lifelong learning, which may include postgraduate education, to successfully adapt to technological, industry specific, and cultural changes and to foster adept functioning in society.

5. Performing engineering practice in a context that reflects awareness of the ethics of their profession and of the impacts of their work on the profession and society at large.

These Program Educational Objectives were developed with input from the program’s educational objectives constituency consisting of employers (including CEEN Industry Advisory Board), graduates of the program, and faculty of the department.

Student Outcomes

Student outcomes are those abilities that a graduate of the computer engineering program will have attained so that he/she can meet the educational objectives established for the program.

At the time of graduation, students in the ECE computer engineering program will have:

a. An ability to apply knowledge of mathematics, science, and engineering.

b. An ability to design and conduct experiments, as well as to analyze and interpret data.

c. An ability to design a system, component, or process to meet desired needs within realistic constraints such as economic, environmental, social, political, ethical, health and safety, manufacturability, and sustainability.

d. An ability to function on multidisciplinary teams.

e. An ability to identify, formulate, and solve engineering problems.

f. An understanding of professional and ethical responsibility.

g. An ability to communicate effectively.

h. The broad education necessary to understand the impact of engineering solutions in a global, economic, environmental, and societal context.

i. A recognition of the need for, and an ability to engage in life-long learning.

j. A knowledge of contemporary issues.

k. An ability to use the techniques, skills, and modern engineering tools necessary for engineering practice.

The individual holding this degree will have advanced knowledge in his or her field of engineering interest and in addition will have a university educational background involving mathematics, the physical sciences, and the humanities and social sciences. Completion of this curriculum will enable the graduate to enter employment in positions involving computer hardware design and applications, computer software design and development, microcomputer based applications, and computer networking. The program also leads to the preparation for graduate work in computer engineering, computer science or electrical engineering.

MAJOR DEPARTMENT ADMISSION

General Requirements

Advisement

Upon entry into the program, each student will be assigned a faculty academic advisor. It is required that the student meet with the advisor prior to each class registration period and that all courses to be applied toward the degree be selected with the advice and approval of the advisor. Students are expected to have their academic records reviewed and obtain approval from the department prior to application to the University registrar for award of the degree in order to insure that all curricular requirements will be satisfied by the time of intended graduation.

Curriculum

Because of the rapid developments in the field of computer engineering, the curricular requirements are continually reviewed and upgraded to reflect technological advances. Curricular sequence and course descriptions contained herein are intended to serve as general guidelines. Contact the department for information on any changes to the requirements that are currently in effect but not listed in this catalog. Currently enrolled students are expected to modify their programs to take advantage of such revisions. Students who do not maintain continuous progress toward the degree through enrollment in applicable course work will be considered as new students upon reentering the computer or electronics engineering curricular sequence and will be subject to the requirements of the curriculum current at the time of their reentry. Certain courses may not be valid as prerequisites or as credit toward the degree after two academic years; the student’s academic advisor should be consulted regarding applicability.

The department maintains a high standard of excellence in meeting its objective of providing the student with extensive experience in the fields of computer engineering and electronics engineering. The development of both hardware and software and the knowledge of the interrelationship of these areas is enhanced through the extensive use of laboratory equipment. The applicable University bulletins and College academic policies must be followed to ensure that the student satisfies the campus general education requirements.

Capstone

The capstone requirement provides a unique and challenging opportunity for the undergraduate student to demonstrate his/her ability to apply the knowledge gained in the course work sequence to the planning, design, execution, testing and reporting of a significant project in the applications of engineering principles. The initiative and responsibility expected of the student executing the senior thesis parallel the expectations of the employer of the program graduate.

Electives

Computer engineering, electrical engineering and electronic engineering courses which are described in the catalog but are not shown as requirements in the semester sequences are offered as the need arises to provide co-interest areas wherein the students may broaden their background in the applications of computer engineering or electronics engineering. In addition, appropriate specified technical electives will be selected to augment the student’s particular area of interest. The applicability of transfer course work with engineering content toward credit in the curriculum is determined on a case-by-case basis by the department.

Special Interest Areas

Opportunities are provided for the development of areas of special interest through enrollment in the Individual Study in Computer and Electronics Engineering courses which are offered at the freshman through senior level for the student who may wish to develop a topic under the guidance of a department faculty member. Enrollment is by permission after approval of a written proposal. Special Topics in Computer and Electronics Engineering classes also are offered by the department as the need arises to cover topics needing emphasis as a result of the rapidly developing fields of computer engineering and electronics engineering. Academic advisors should be consulted regarding the particular topics to be covered and the necessary prerequisites for each offering of this course.

Students who expect to continue their education at the graduate level after the award of the baccalaureate degree should consult their advisor regarding course selections that would enhance that objective.

Students are encouraged to develop their professional and leadership potential through participation in student chapters of related professional organizations and in University extracurricular activities. Participation in the University Honors Program is encouraged for those who qualify.

MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Requirements for the Degree

First Semester

ECEN 103 Computer & Electronics Engineering Fundamentals 4

CSCE 155A Computer Science I or CSCE 155E Computer Science I: Systems Engineering Focus 3

MATH 106 Calculus I 5

ACE Elective SLO 5 3

Total 15

Second Semester

ECEN 106 Microprocessor Applications 3

ECEN 194 Special Topics in Computer & Electronics Engineering I 1

ECEN 225 Computer & Electronics Engineering Seminar 1

CSCE 156 Computer Science II 4

MATH 107 Calculus II* 4

PHYS 211 General Physics I 4

Total 17

*Calculus II is a 5-credit course on the Omaha Campus. Students taking Calculus II on the Lincoln Campus will need to obtain an additional 1 credit hour of math or science.

Third Semester

ECEN 213 Electrical Circuits I 3

ECEN 218 Electrical Circuits Lab 1

MATH 221 Differential Equations 3

PHYS 212 General Physics II 4

PHYS 222 General Physics Lab II 1

COMM 109 Fundamentals of Human Communication 3

Total 15

Fourth Semester

ECEN 222 Electronic Circuits I 4

ECEN 313 Switching Circuits Theory 4

JGEN 300 Technical Communication II 3

MATH 208 Calculus III 4

ECEN 2170 Electrical Circuits III 1

Total 16

Fifth Semester

ECEN 310 Digital Design & Interfacing 4

ECEN 332 Assembly Language Programming 1

CSCE 310 Data Structures & Algorithms 3

MATH 314 Linear Algebra 3

MATH 380 Statistics & Applications (STAT 380) 3

Total 14

Sixth Semester

ECEN 325 Communications Systems 4

ECEN 433 Microprocessor System Design 4

ENGR Electives 6

ACE Elective SLO 6 3

Total 17

Seventh Semester

ECEN 435 Embedded Microcontroller Design 4

ECEN 496 Capstone I 2

ENGR 469 Tech, Science & Civ (UNO) 3

ENGR Electives 3

ACE Elective SLO 7 3

Total 15

Eighth Semester

ECEN 499 Capstone II 3

ENGR Electives 6

ACE Electives SLO 8 & 9 6

Total 15

NOTE: Three hours of the engineering electives can be chosen from a list of approved non-ECEN courses.

Total Credit Hours Required 124

ADDITIONAL MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Grade Rules

Student must have a grade of C or better in ECEN 2130 and ECEN 3130 before taking any course which has these coures as prerequisites.

Construction Engineering

COLLEGE: Engineering

MAJOR: Construction Engineering

DEGREE OFFERED: Bachelor of Science in Construction Engineering

HOURS REQUIRED: 125

MINIMUM CUMULATIVE GPA: 2.4 for graduation

MINOR AVAILABLE: No

ADVISOR: Garrett Gassman (Omaha), Kevin Sueper (Lincoln)

DESCRIPTION

Durham School of Architectural Engineering and Construction

School Director: Jay Puckett

Program Coordinator: Kevin Grosskopf

Professors: Foster, Goedert, Morcous

Associate Professors: Bernstein, Bonsell, Jensen, Norton, Schwer, Stentz

Assistant Professors: Ahn, Esmaeili, Woldesenbet

Construction engineering (CONE) is a program of the Charles W. Durham School of Architectural Engineering and Construction. The construction engineering major integrates engineering, construction and management courses. This program is designed for persons fulfilling the construction industry’s need for licensed professional engineers. It resembles the construction management program but provides a greater emphasis on engineering, scientific, and technical courses to meet requirements for licensure as a professional engineer. The courses focus on the application of engineering principles to solve real-world construction problems. They include instruction in civil engineering, structural principles, material testing and evaluation, project management, computer-assisted design, 3D animation, sustainability and graphic communication.

The Durham School Construction Engineering program is accredited by EAC-ABET, Inc.

The educational objectives of the construction engineering program are to produce graduates who will (in three to five years after graduation):

Possess knowledge acquisition skills enabling them to remain current throughout their careers;
Apply engineering principles of analysis and design to the systems being constructed;
Employ technical skills with innovation and dedication to pursue improved functionality, increased efficiency and decreased costs;
Use communication skills to effectively share their ideas with many forms of media;
Adapt to the constantly changing, interdisciplinary design and construction fields by applying teamwork and team building skills; and
Apply appropriate construction practices including business organization, estimating, scheduling, project delivery and ethics.

Under the stimulus of increasing demand for global services, many Nebraska companies have expanded their reach well beyond U.S. borders. This demand gives the construction engineering graduate an unprecedented number of opportunities for employment (locally, nationally, and internationally), and for pursuing an advanced degree at UNL or elsewhere.

Construction engineers participate in the preparation of engineering and architectural documents, including specifications, which they translate into finished projects, such as buildings for housing, commerce and industry, highways, railroads, waterways, airports, power plants, energy distribution systems, military bases and space center complexes. These projects involve thousands of details shared by a team of owners, architects, engineers, general constructors, specialty constructors, manufacturers, material suppliers, equipment distributors, regulatory bodies and agencies, labor resources and others. The constructor assumes responsibility for delivery of the completed project at a specified time and cost and also accepts associated legal, financial and management obligations. Because of the broad scope of the construction engineer’s project responsibility, he/she must assure the project’s constructability as well as its capability to be operated and maintained.

Construction engineering students are required to enroll in a set of courses specifically designed for a general construction education. Each student selects, with the guidance of an advisor, a set of approved electives. The program outlined below leads to the bachelor of science degree in construction engineering.

MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Requirements for the Degree (Lincoln campus)

First Semester

CHEM 109 General Chemistry I 4

COMM 286 Business & Professional Communication 3

CONE 103 Introduction to Construction Engineering 1

CSCE 155N Computer Science I: Engineering & Science Focus 3

ENGR 10 Freshman Engineering Seminar 0

MATH 106 Calculus I 5

Total 16

Second Semester

MATH 107 Calculus II 4

JGEN 200 Technical Communication I 3

PHYS 211 General Physics I 4

PHYS 221 General Physics I Lab 1

ACE Elective 3

Choose one course from not yet satisfied ACE outcomes 5, 7, or 9.

Total 15

Third Semester

CIVE 221 Geometric Control Systems (CONE 221) 3

CNST 225 Introduction to Building Information Modeling 3

ENGR 20 Sophomore Engineering Seminar 0

MATH 208 Calculus III 4

MECH 223 Engineering Statics 3

PHYS 212 General Physics II 4

Total 17

Fourth Semester

CONE 211 Construction Business Methods 3

BSEN 206 Engineering Economics (CONE 206) 3

MATH 221 Differential Equations 3

MECH 325 Mechanics of Elastic Bodies 3

MECH 373 Engineering Dynamics 3

Total 15

Fifth Semester

CIVE 341 Introduction to Structural Engineering 4

CONE 319 Construction Methods & Equipment 3

CONE 378 Construction Estimating (CNST 378) 3

MATH 380 Statistics & Applications (STAT 380) or MECH 321 Engineering Statistics & Data Analysis 3

MECH 310 Fluid Mechanics (CIVE 310) 3

Total 16

Sixth Semester

CIVE 334 Introduction to Geotechnical Engineering 4

CIVE 378 Materials of Construction 3

ECON 212 Principles of Microeconomics 3

ELEC 211 Elements of Electrical Engineering I 3

ACE Elective 3

Choose one course from not yet satisfied ACE outcomes 5, 7, or 9.

Total 16

Seventh Semester

CIVE 440 Reinforced Concrete Design I 3

CONE 414 Accident Prevention in Construction or CNST 444 Construction Site Safety Management 3

CONE 476 Project Budgets & Controls (CNST 476) 3

CONE 485 Construction Planning, Scheduling & Controls (CNST 485) 3

Technical Elective 3

Total 15

Eighth Semester

CIVE 441 Steel Design I 3

CONE 489 Construction Engineering Capstone Course 3

BLAW 371 Legal Environment 3

Technical Elective 3

ACE Elective 3

Choose one course from not yet satisfied ACE outcomes 5, 7, or 9.

Total 15

Total Credit Hours Required for Graduation 125

ADDITIONAL MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Grade Rules

C- and D Grades

All course work must be of C grade level or higher to be credited toward graduation requirements or to be valid as a prerequisite for another course.

Electives

Students are required to enroll in a predetermined set of courses specifically designed for general construction education. Each student selects, with the approval of his/her advisor, a set of approved electives.

Technical electives are selected from the following list. One (3 credit hour) of the required two electives needs to be considered a design technical elective.

Design Technical Electives

CONE 416 Wood/Contemporary Materials Design

CONE 417 Formwork Systems

CONE 481 Highway & Bridge Construction

CONE 483 Support of Excavation

CIVE 443 Structural Analysis

CIVE 444 Structural Design & Planning

CIVE 446 Steel Design II

CIVE 447 Reinforced Concrete Design II

Technical Electives

All previously listed Design Technical Electives

CNST 379 Construction Estimating II

CNST 434 The Design/Build Project Delivery System

CONE 450 Sustainable Construction

CONE 466 Heavy/Civil Estimating

CONE 498 Special Topics in Construction

MECH 420 Heat Transfer

ACE Requirements

The CONE program follows the UNL ACE general education requirements. Because of the specific needs of the program, several of these courses are specified in the curriculum. Please contact Melissa Hoffman at melissa.hoffman@unl.edu or 402-554-4482, if you are interested in more information about this program.

Geography

COLLEGE: Arts & Sciences

MAJOR: Geography

DEGREE OFFERED: Bachelor of Arts or Bachelor of Science

HOURS REQUIRED: 120

MINIMUM CUMULATIVE GPA: 2.0 for graduation

MINOR AVAILABLE: Yes

ADVISOR: Rebecca Buller

DESCRIPTION

Program Lead: Paul Hanson

Professors: Archer, Wishart

Associate Professors: Hanson, Wardlow, Zygielbaum

Assistant Professor of Practice: Buller

Emeritus Professors: Amedeo, Lawson, Rundquist, Stoddard

Lecturer: Nashleanas

Undergraduate Academic Advisor: Rebecca Buller, rbuller2@unl.edu

Geography is especially appealing to those having interests in travel, learning about other peoples and cultures, and understanding the environment from a systems perspective. The program of geography offers a variety of courses leading to the bachelor of arts (B.A.) and bachelor of science (B.S.) degrees in geography. The objectives of these programs are: 1) to support the goals of a broad liberal education by increasing awareness of the spatial, regional, and environmental aspects of the earth and its peoples; and 2) to provide a specialized knowledge of environmental processes, human-environment relations, American and foreign areas and cultures, and geographic techniques such as cartography, remote sensing and geographic information analysis.

Students may specialize in one of many areas, including climate and weather, cultural/human geography, geographic information systems, historical geography of the Great Plains, natural resources, physical geography, pre-community and regional planning, regional studies, or remote sensing.

An education in geography prepares students for careers in government agencies as well as those involved with foreign service, land management, tourism, health care delivery systems, environmental assessment, transportation development, land use planning, air traffic control, GIS and cartographic analysis, and in a wide variety of businesses, particularly those concerned with environmental mapping, geographic information systems, and planning. A geography major also prepares students for graduate-level degrees in geography, law (especially environmental law), international business, urban and regional planning, and teaching at all levels.

Major in Geography

The major in geography consists of seven mandatory courses with a common core in human-environment relations. Students should begin their programs with introductory physical and human courses, then move to courses dealing with environmental issues, world regions, and courses in techniques of acquiring, mapping and displaying geographic data. An undergraduate seminar which covers historical and philosophical aspects of geography as well as practical matters such as jobs and graduate schools, completes the set of mandatory courses. Beyond this core of required courses are 8 hours of electives.

Graduate Work. The advanced degrees of master of arts and doctor of philosophy in geography are offered. For details on these programs, see the Graduate Studies Bulletin.

MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

The major entails a total of 30 hours, of which 14 hours must be numbered 300 or above.

Core Requirements 16

GEOG 140 Introductory Human Geography or GEOG 120 Introductory Economic Geography 3

GEOG 155 Elements of Physical Geography 4

GEOG 181 Quality of the Environment 3

GEOG 272 Geography of World Regions 3

GEOG 402 Undergraduate Seminar (Senior Seminar) 3

Specific Major Requirements

Geography Techniques Courses 6

(6 hours from the following list,with at least 3 hours numbered 400 or above)

ANTH 387 GIS in Archaeology

CRPL 432 Advanced Spatial Analysis with GIS

CRPL 495 Selected Topics in Community & Regional Planning: Planning with GIS

GEOG 217 Mapping Science in the 21st Century

GEOG 312 Introduction to Geospatial Information Sciences

GEOG 317 Cartography I: Introduction to Cartography

GEOG 412 Introduction to Geographic Information Systems (GIS)

GEOG 414 Quantitative Methods in Geography

GEOG 415 Introduction to Computer Mapping

GEOG 417 Cartography II: Electronic Atlas Design & Production

GEOG 418 Introduction to Remote Sensing

GEOG 419 Applications of Remote Sensing in Agriculture & Natural Resources

GEOG 420 Digital Image Analysis of Remote Sensing Data

GEOG 421 Field Techniques in Remote Sensing

GEOG 422 Advanced Techniques in Geographic Information Systems

GEOG 425 Scientific Visualization in Cartography

GEOG 427 Introduction to the Global Positioning System (GPS)

GEOG 432 GIS Programming for Advanced Spatial Analysis & Modeling

GEOG 444 Geo-demographics & GIS

GEOG 461 Geospatial Approaches in Digital Humanities & Social Sciences

GEOG 483 Cognitive Processes in Map Comprehension & Use

GEOG 498 Advanced Special Problems: Atlas Composition & Design

Geography Electives 8

8 hours of electives typically remain after the required and technique courses are completed to meet the 30 hour major requirement.

Students may choose to specialize in one of many areas, including climate and weather, cultural/human geography, geographic information systems, historical geography of the Great Plains, natural resources, physical geography, pre-community and regional planning, regional studies, or remote sensing.

Additional courses not formally cross-listed as GEOG might apply towards GEOG credit by approval of advisor.

Program Assessment. In order to assist the department in evaluating the effectiveness of its programs, majors will be required to complete written and oral examinations in the Senior Seminar, GEOG 402, over knowledge in all components of the major, as well as over more detailed knowledge in the student’s area of focus. Students will be informed of the scheduling and format of assessment exams in the Senior Seminar. Students will also be given exit interviews prior to graduation to gather their views on the effectiveness of the major. Results of participation in this assessment activity will in no way affect a student’s GPA or graduation.

ADDITIONAL MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Course Level Requirement

Of the total 30 hours, 14 hours must be numbered 300 or above. Of the 6 hours of techniques courses, 3 hours must be numbered 400 or above.

Grade Rules

No grade lower than a C may count toward the major. No more than 6 hours may be taken Pass/No Pass.

REQUIREMENTS FOR MINOR OFFERED BY DEPARTMENT

18 hours of GEOG courses, including 10 hours in courses numbered 300 or above.

Graphic Design

COLLEGE: Fine & Performing Arts

MAJOR: Graphic Design

DEGREE OFFERED: Bachelor of Arts

HOURS REQUIRED: 120

MINIMUM CUMULATIVE GPA: 2.0 for graduation

MINOR AVAILABLE: No

ADVISOR: Christy Aggens

DESCRIPTION

Director: Robert Derr, 120 Richards Hall
Professors: Derr, Fritz, Kunc, Pinnell, Souto
Associate Professors: Bohls, Cal, Dominguez, Holz, Ingraham, Williams
Assistant Professors: Asher, Pickering, Sontheimer, Sutherlen
Assistant Professors of Practice: Syron

Bachelor of Arts Degree at a Glance
ACE Requirements 30
Languages: Classical & Modern 0-6
Select from the list of “Approved Courses” found under “College Degree Requirements.”
Graphic Design Major Requirements 57
Minors 18-24
Electives 3-15
Total Hours Required for Graduation 120
Bachelor of Fine Arts Degree at a Glance
ACE Requirements 30
Art Major Requirements 84
Electives 6
Total Hours Required for Graduation 120

The graphic design major prepares students to integrate creativity with visual communication to create a wide variety of print and digital products. The School of Art, Art History and Design offers two undergraduate degrees for this major. Both include a solid base of knowledge in the principles and history of art and design. The bachelor of arts (BA) degree, with nearly fifty percent of its courses in the major, requires students to complement this foundation with another area of study. The bachelor of fine arts (BFA) degree expands on the basic course work by providing additional experience in graphic design and related studio art areas. This intensive degree holds seventy percent of its courses in the major and is intended for those who want to work in a design career or pursue graduate study in graphic design.

The graphic design major prepares students to integrate creativity with visual communication to create a wide variety of print and digital products. The School of Art, Art History & Design offers two undergraduate degrees for this major. Both include a solid base of knowledge in the principles and history of art and design. The bachelor of arts (BA) degree, with nearly fifty percent of its courses in the major, requires students to complement this foundation with another area of study. The bachelor of fine arts (BFA) degree expands on the basic course work by providing additional experience in graphic design and related studio art areas. This intensive degree holds seventy percent of its courses in the major and is intended for those who want to work in a design career or pursue graduate study in graphic design.

The graphic design major prepares students to integrate creativity with visual communication to create a wide variety of print and digital products. The School of Art, Art History & Design offers two undergraduate degrees for this major. Both include a solid base of knowledge in the principles and history of art and design. The bachelor of arts (BA) degree, with nearly fifty percent of its courses in the major, requires students to complement this foundation with another area of study. The bachelor of fine arts (BFA) degree expands on the basic course work by providing additional experience in graphic design and related studio art areas. This intensive degree holds seventy percent of its courses in the major and is intended for those who want to work in a design career or pursue graduate study in graphic design.

MAJOR DEPARTMENT ADMISSION

Any student who meets college admission requirements may declare a major in graphic design.

MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Bachelor of Arts Requirements
BA Requirements 57
Required Foundation 12
ARTP 151 Color and Composition 3
ARTP 152 Three-Dimensional Design 3
DRAW 201 Drawing 3
DRAW 202 Life Drawing 3

GRPH 428 Design Studio II: Design Capstone 3

Graphic Design Courses 18

GRPH 221 Graphic Design I 3
GRPH 222 Creative and Critical Thinking 3
GRPH 223 Typography I 3
GRPH 224 Design History and Practice 3
GRPH 321 Graphic Design II 3
GRPH 325 Interaction Design I 3
GRPH 421 Graphic Design III 3
GRPH 426 Design Studio I 3
Graphic Design Electives 6

Art History 12
AHIS 101 Cave Paintings to Cathedrals 3
AHIS 102 Renaissance to Modern Art 3
Art History electives (including a minimum of 3 credits in courses numbered above 299) 6

Minor Requirements
BA students are required to complete a minimum of one minor. A second major can be used to satisfy the minor requirement.

Bachelor of Fine Arts Requirements
BFA Requirements 84
Required Foundation 12
ARTP 151 Color and Composition 3
ARTP 152 Three-Dimensional Design 3
DRAW 201 Drawing 3
DRAW 202 Life Drawing 3

GRPH 428 Design Studio II: Design Capstone 3

Graphic Design Courses 18

GRPH 221 Graphic Design I 3
GRPH 222 Creative and Critical Thinking 3
GRPH 223 Typography I 3
GRPH 224 Design History and Practice 3
GRPH 321 Graphic Design II 3
GRPH 323 Typography II 3
GRPH 325 Interaction Design I 3
GRPH 421 Graphic Design III 3
GRPH 425 Interaction Design II: Interactive Storytelling 3
GRPH 426 Design Studio I 3

Graphic Design Electives 15

Studio Art Electives 12

Select from the following areas: ceramics, drawing, painting, photography, printmaking, sculpture, special topics, Gallery Management, Art at Cedar Point(excludes foundation courses)

Art History 12
AHIS 101 Cave Paintings to Cathedrals 3
AHIS 102 Renaissance to Modern Art 3
Art History electives (including a minimum of 3 credits in courses numbered above 299) 6

ADDITIONAL MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

BA Degree
Grade Rules
C- and D Grades
Minimum grade for all major requirements is C.
Pass/No Pass Limits
All courses taken for major requirements must be for letter grade, unless the course is only offered Pass/No Pass.
Course Level Requirement
A minimum of 3 credits of studio art and 3 credits of art history must be taken in courses numbered above 299.
Extended Education, Independent Study Rules, Internship Credit Rules, Transfer Credit Rules
No more than 6 hours of independent study courses may count toward the major in the BA degree. This includes all courses numbered 390, 392, 395, 396, 490, 492, 495, 496, and 499H offered by the School of Art, Art History and Design.
At least 15 credit hours in studio art and 9 credit hours in art history of the required BA courses must be taken at UNL. Courses taken at other academic institutions may be substituted for the remaining required courses subject to evaluation by the department.
Time and Credit Guidelines
The School of Art, Art History and Design adheres to the following time and credit guidelines established by the National Association of Schools of Art and Design (NASAD):
In studio courses, one hour of credit represents three hours of work each week of the 16-week semester. Two of the hours are spent in class with the instructor, and one hour of additional work is expected outside of regularly scheduled class time.
In lecture/discussion courses, one hour of credit represents one hour each week in class, and two hours each week of work outside of class for the duration of the 16-week semester.
BFA Degree
Grade Rules
C- and D Grades
Minimum grade for all major requirements is C.
Pass/No Pass Limits
All courses taken for major requirements must be for letter grade, unless the course is only offered Pass/No Pass.
Course Level Requirement
A minimum of 3 credits of art history must be taken in courses numbered above 299.
Extended Education, Independent Study Rules, Internship Credit Rules, Transfer Credit Rules
No more than 9 hours of independent study courses may count toward the major in the BA degree. This includes all courses numbered 390, 392, 395, 396, 490, 492, 495, 496, and 499H offered by the School of Art, Art History and Design.
At least 36 credit hours in studio art and 6 credit hours in art history of the required BFA courses must be taken at UNL. Courses taken at other academic institutions may be substituted for the remaining required courses subject to evaluation by the department.
Time and Credit Guidelines
The School of Art, Art History and Design adheres to the following time and credit guidelines established by the National Association of Schools of Art and Design (NASAD):
In studio courses, 1 hour of credit represents three hours of work each week of the 16-week semester. Two of the hours are spent in class with the instructor, and one hour of additional work is expected outside of regularly scheduled class time.
In lecture/discussion courses, 1 hour of credit represents one hour each week in class, and two hours each week of work outside of class for the duration of the 16-week semester.

REQUIREMENTS FOR MINOR OFFERED BY DEPARTMENT

Pre-Law

COLLEGE: Exploratory & Pre-Professional Advising Center

MAJOR: Pre-Law

DEGREE OFFERED: Non-degree seeking

HOURS REQUIRED: N/A

MINIMUM CUMULATIVE GPA: N/A

MINOR AVAILABLE: N/A

ADVISOR: Exploratory and Pre-Professional Advising Center

DESCRIPTION

The pre-law area of study is an advising category used to identify students advancing toward a law-related career goal. Students cannot declare a major or earn a degree in the pre-law area. Most students use their undergraduate academic program to develop the desired skill set for entry into law school and the legal profession. Students may select any UNL academic major while pursuing a pre-law area of study, and can temporarily select a major of “Pre-Law” through the Exploratory and Pre-Professional Advising Center (Explore Center) while they are exploring and determining which academic major they would like to declare.

Students pursuing a pre-law area of study can receive guidance and advice from the Explore Center by declaring the pre-law category with their college advising office.

Pre-Law

Law is the system we use to ensure order and justice for individuals and communities within our society. The broad nature of the legal field allows people to work with the law in a number of ways. Litigation (trial practice), representative practice, legal planning, education, and adjudication (becoming a judge) are traditional ways in which people work directly with the law. However, a legal education is useful and may be applied to a variety of other fields such as business, insurance, government, writing, resource management, or publishing.

High School Preparation

Students planning to pursue advanced work in the pre-law program should begin with a strong college preparatory course program in high school. In addition to meeting the University entrance requirements, it is recommended that pre-law students finish four years of the same foreign language in high school.

ADMISSION

Program Admission

Students who have met the overall University admission requirements established by the Board of Regents are eligible for admission to the Explore Center. The University admission requirements are outlined in detail on the Admissions website at http://admissions.unl.edu/.

Some UNL colleges have admission requirements in addition to the overall University admission requirements, and pre-law students will be advised accordingly as they choose the majors they would like to pursue.

Admission Deficiencies/Removal of Deficiencies

Because admission requirements establish the level of knowledge and skills which are needed for a student to succeed at UNL, students who are admitted with core course deficiencies in foreign language and geometry are expected to quickly remove them. Deficiencies must be removed before a student is eligible for graduation.

ADVISING

Professional academic advisors in the Explore Center engage pre-law students in major exploration, degree planning, and academic course work selection processes. By working closely with all of the UNL colleges, Explore Center advisors can help students design a general academic plan for one or more semesters that will allow them to progress toward a degree, while also exploring the variety of opportunities offered by the University. Students are encouraged to enroll in exploratory courses to help identify majors of interest. Additionally, all UNL students are required to complete the Achievement-Centered Education (ACE) requirements (for more information see http://ace.unl.edu).

Pre-law students are encouraged to meet with a professional academic advisor in the Explore Center early in their first semester at UNL to discuss interest areas and to develop a plan for major exploration. Pre-law students should continue to meet with an Explore Center advisor at least once per semester and participate in Explore Center workshops until they have declared their major. Additional information concerning major exploration can be found on the Explore Center (http://explorecenter.unl.edu) and Career Services (http://www.unl.edu/careers/explore) websites.

Students are assigned to a professional academic advisor in the Explore Center but may see any advisor in the Center. Professional advisors in the Explore Center are available on an appointment and/or walk-in basis Monday through Friday in 127 Love (Library) South and can be reached at 402-472-3605 or explorecenter@unl.edu.

ACADEMIC POLICIES

Academic Load

Pre-law students may enroll in a maximum of 18 credits in the fall and spring semesters. Students should refer to the Office of the University Registrar's website at http://registrar.unl.edu to determine the number of credits they may enroll in for each of the summer sessions.

Grade Rules

Pass/No Pass Limits

The Pass/No Pass grading option was designed to enable students to take courses in areas of interest where they may feel they have had minimal preparation without adversely affecting their grade point average. Grades of P (pass) are interpreted as a grade of C or better. Neither grade P or NP (no pass) contributes to the grade point average.

Pre-law students should always seek assistance from an Explore Center advisor in determining whether they should take a course through the Pass/No Pass option. Students may or may not be able to take courses Pass/No Pass depending on their intended majors.

Student Recognition

Pre-law students who complete at least 12 graded semester hours with a 3.60 GPA are eligible for the Explore Center List of Distinguished Students.

Transfer Credit Rules

The Explore Center does not offer a degree and advisors do not make transfer evaluation decisions. The determination of which transfer courses will meet graduation requirements in a specific college cannot be made until the student declares a specific major within one of the UNL undergraduate degree-granting colleges.

Pre-Veterinary Medicine

COLLEGE: Agricultural Sciences & Natural Resources

MAJOR: Pre-Veterinary Medicine

DEGREE OFFERED: Non-degree program

HOURS REQUIRED: 60-70

MINIMUM CUMULATIVE GPA: Usually 2.50

MINOR AVAILABLE: No

ADVISOR: Roberto Cortinas

DESCRIPTION

Director and Associate Dean: Clayton L. Kelling, School of Veterinary Medicine and Biomedical Sciences, 120C Vet Basic Sciences

Head: Clinton Krehbiel, Department of Animal Sciences, C203 Animal Science

The Nebraska Pre-Veterinary Medicine program (PVET) is designed for students who want to become veterinarians. The Doctor of Veterinary Medicine (DVM) degree, or its equivalent, must be earned to become a veterinarian. Students wishing to earn the DVM degree must first successfully complete the undergraduate Pre-Veterinary Medicine program to qualify for admission to a veterinary school that awards the DVM degree.

The Nebraska PVET program can help students qualify for admission to any of the American Veterinary Medical Association Council on Education (AVMA-COE)-accredited veterinary schools which offer the DVM degree or its equivalent. Students completing our PVET program do not earn baccalaureate degrees nor are they guaranteed admission to any veterinary school.

There are three general PVET requirements for admission to veterinary schools: academic, career exploration, and leadership development. Applicants are assessed in each of those areas during the application process.

Academic requirements include specific undergraduate courses that must be successfully completed, and course and cumulative grade point averages (GPAs). The specific courses included in a PVET program are specified by each of the veterinary schools. There is not standard curriculum, so each veterinary school publishes its PVET course requirements. The undergraduate courses included in our PVET program are those for the Professional Program in Veterinary Medicine (PPVM), however, our PVET program can be modified so that a student can qualify academically for admission to any AVMA-COE accredited veterinary school. The PVET course requirements for other veterinary schools may be found on those schools’ websites. A list of AVMA-accredited veterinary school may be obtained on the AVMA website at https://www.avma.org/ProfessionalDevelopment/Education/Accreditation/Colleges/Documents/colleges_accredited.pdf.

Veterinary schools require that their applicants attain a minimum cumulative GPA to be considered for admission. The PPVM requires a cumulative GPA of at least a 2.50 for application consideration. Minimum cum GPA requirements for other veterinary schools may be found on their respective websites.

The veterinary medical career exploration requirement is intended to help PVET students to learn what veterinarians do professionally and that is usually done by working in a veterinary clinic in either a paid or unpaid status. Students may also explore other aspects of veterinary medicine, including government service, academic or industrial research, or military service. It is recommended that students develop a professional relationship with a veterinarian so that veterinarian may write a good letter of recommendation in support of that student's application to veterinary school.

As stated previously, completion of the PVET program does not earn the student a baccalaureate degree. We recommend that students wishing to become veterinarians start as a PVET major so they can take every advantage of our PVET advising program. Our PVET advisors will help their advisees reach their academic and career goals. We strongly recommend that PVET students declare a degree-granting major, such as Veterinary Science, Animal Science, Fisheries & Wildlife, or biochemistry, and pursue a baccalaureate degree while completing the PVET requirements. One baccalaureate degree does not provide an advantage for admission to a veteirnary school compared to others. The student may choose any baccalaureate program that is of interest to the student.

Expect to spend 2-3 years completing the PVET program. If the student is not prepared to start the science-intensive PVET program, its completion will take longer. Adequate preparation includes math proficiency, as indicated by the Nebraska Math Proficiency Examination (MPE). Students who do not place into at least MATH 102 – College Trigonometry may take longer to complete the PVET program and baccalaureate degree.

Additional requirements for the pre-vet program:

Pass/No Pass credits are not accepted. Pre-Vet courses must be taken for a grade, unless the course is only offered Pass/No Pass.

A grade of C or better is necessary to fulfill the pre-vet requirement. If a course is repeated to obtain a higher grade or to earn a grade of C or better, some professional programs may consider the average of all grades earned for that course. Other programs may consider the highest grade or the most recent grade. Check the policy of each veterinary school to which application is to be made.

The acceptability of AP, CLEP, or IB earned credits varies by veterinary school. It is important for each student to check the policies of the veterinary school to which application is to be made.

MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

PPVM Pre-Veterinary Medicine Core

NOTE: What follows fulfills the PVET requirements for the Professional Program in Veterinary Medicine (PPVM), a cooperative program between the University of Nebraska–Lincoln and Iowa State University. Criteria for admission to that program may be found on the PPVM website at http://vetmed.unl.edu/prospectivestudents. This program may be modified so that a student may qualify academically for admission to any American Veterinary Medical Association Council on Education-accredited veternary school. Students planning to attend other veterinary schools must check with those schools to determine the differences between the other veterinary school and the PPVM PVET requirements.

College Integrative Course 3

SCIL 101 Science and Decision-Making for a Complex World 3

Veterinary Science 1

VBMS 101 Success in Veterinary Science 1

Natural Science Courses 39-43

Life Sciences 8

LIFE 120 & LIFE 120L Fundamentals of Biology I & Lab (ACE 4) 4

LIFE 121 & LIFE 121L Fundamentals of Biology II & Lab (ACE 4) 4

NOTE: BIOS 101/101L and BIOS 112/112L or their equivalents will not satisfy this requirement.

Genetics 4

AGRO 315 Genetics or BIOS 206 General Genetics 4

Anatomy and Physiology 4-9

Select from the following courses, one in either physiology or anatomy is required, but one course in each subject area is recommended:

ASCI 340 Animal Physiological Systems (4 cr);

or BIOS 213/213L Human Physiology and lab (4 cr) ;

or BIOS 214 Human Anatomy (5 cr);

or VBMS 307 Introduction to Veterinary Anatomy (4 cr)

Chemistry 15

CHEM 109 General Chemistry I (ACE 4) 4

CHEM 110 General Chemistry II (ACE 4) 4

CHEM 251 Organic Chemistry I 3

CHEM 252 Organic Chemistry II 3

CHEM 253 Organic Chemistry I Lab or CHEM 254 Organic Chemistry II Lab 1

Physics 5

Select from:

PHYS 141 Elementary General Physics I (ACE 4) (5 cr)

PHYS 211 & PHYS 221 General Physics I & Lab (5 cr)

NOTE: PHYS 151 and MSYM 109/109L do not meet the requirement.

Biological Chemistry 3

Select from:

BIOC 321 Elements of Biochemistry (3 cr)

BIOC 431 Biomolecules & Metabolism (BIOS 431/CHEM 431) (3 cr)

Mathematics and Statistics 5

Five credit hours beyond MATH 101 College Algebra

Select from:

MATH 102 Trigonometry (2 cr)

MATH 103 College Algebra & Trigonometry (5 cr) (only 2 credit hours apply)

MATH 104 Applied Calculus (3 cr)

MATH 106 Calculus I (5 cr)

STAT 218 Introduction to Statistics (ACE 3) (3 cr)

Communications 9

Written Communication (ACE 1) 6

Select two from:

ENGL 150 Writing & Inquiry (3 cr)

ENGL 151 Writing & Argument (3 cr)

ENGL 254 Writing & Communities (3 cr)

JGEN 120 Basic Business Communication (3 cr)

JGEN 200 Technical Communication I (3 cr)

JGEN 300 Technical Communication II (3 cr)

Oral Communication (ACE 2) 3

Select one from:

ALEC 102 Interpersonal Skills for Leadership (3 cr)

COMM 101 Communication in the 21st Century

COMM 109 or 109H Fundamentals of Human Communication

COMM 209 or 209H Public Speaking

COMM 283 Interpersonal Communication

COMM 286 Business and Professional Communication

or any ACE 2 course

Economics (ACE 6) 3

Select one from:

AECN 141 Introduction to the Economics of Agriculture (3 cr)

ECON 200 Economic Essentials and Issues (3 cr)

ECON 211/ECON 211H Principles of Macroeconomics (3 cr)

ECON 212/ECON 212H Principles of Microeconomics (3 cr)

ACE Courses 12

Select one course each from ACE outcomes 5, 7, 8, and 9.

ADDITIONAL MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Grade Rules

All courses taken to meet PVET requirements must be taken for a letter grade, unless the course is offered only pass/no pass.

Most veterinary schools require a grade of at least a C in each PVET course. Exact PVET course grade requirements for admission should be determined for each veterinary school to which application is to be made.

A minimum cumulative GPA of 2.50 is generally required for application to a veterinary school. The exact GPA requirement for admission should be obtained for each veterinary school to which application is to be made.

Speech-Language Pathology

COLLEGE: Education & Human Sciences

MAJOR: Speech-Language Pathology

DEGREE OFFERED: Bachelor of Science in Education & Human Sciences

HOURS REQUIRED: 120

MINIMUM CUMULATIVE GPA: 2.50 for graduation

MINOR AVAILABLE: No

ADVISOR: Cameya Ramirez-Rousseau and Amanda Bergeron-Bauer

DESCRIPTION

The bachelor of science in communication sciences and disorders provides the preprofessional courses required for graduate study in either speech-language pathology or audiology. The entry level for practice as a speech-language pathologist requires a masters degree in speech-language pathology. A doctorate of audiology (AuD) is required to practice audiology. Upon completion of degree and licensure/certification requirements, a person may work in a variety of settings including schools or other education agencies, medical clinics or other medical/nursing facilities, health agencies, or private practice.

General Information

The College offers undergraduate programs leading to a bachelor of science in education and human sciences degree in more than 40 different teaching endorsements. Some students in other UNL colleges choose to seek certification, completing a degree in their home college while meeting all requirements for teacher certification in the College of Education and Human Sciences.

Early field placement in public and private schools is a nationally recognized hallmark of the teacher education program in the College of Education and Human Sciences. While internships are a valuable enhancement to many students’ education, in the College of Education and Human Sciences, practicum experiences and student teaching are a critical and essential part of the teacher education curriculum and these must be successfully completed. A student’s inability to complete these field experiences, for any reason, may adversely impact the candidate’s ability to gain admission into the College or maintain enrollment in a teacher preparation program. Students unlikely or unable to complete the field experience may be counseled to seek other opportunities where success is more attainable. (See “Criminal History Background Check Requirement” and “Professional and Ethical Behavior” under the OTHER heading for additional information with respect to behaviors impacting field experience participation.)

Teacher education endorsements are divided into field endorsements or single-subject endorsements. Field endorsements certify the candidate to teach a broader range of courses compared to single-subject endorsements, which certify the candidate to teach in one subject area only. Consequently, a teacher holding a field endorsement is typically more marketable than a teacher holding a single-subject endorsement.

Candidates may also elect to complete requirements for supplemental endorsements; these are additional endorsements that can be added to a field or single-subject endorsement but cannot be taken alone. Supplemental endorsements require additional credit hours beyond those needed for the first endorsement (field or single-subject). Teachers may increase their marketability by adding supplemental endorsements.

Students may also choose to complete requirements for two endorsements simultaneously. Completing a second endorsement will require additional credit hours beyond those required for the first endorsement. Often the completion of two endorsements requires more than 120 credit hours of course work and may require additional semesters of course work. Students may contact the College Student Services Center, 105 Henzlik Hall, or their advisor, for assistance in deciding whether to complete: field or single-subject endorsements, one or more supplemental endorsements, or multiple endorsements.

ADMISSION

Admission to the College of Education and Human Sciences does not guarantee admission into a teacher education program. Admission into the undergraduate pre-professional training program in Communication Sciences and Disorders does not guarantee admission into graduate school. Graduate programs have competitive admission requirements. To stay on track in the program, student must:

1. Complete courses by certain times in sequence.

2. Maintain an average of 3.0 or better across SLPA courses

3. Have a cumlative GPA of 3.0 or better by the end of year 2 in program.

MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Endorsement Requirements

Degree at a Glance

ACE Requirements 32-41

ACE 1. ENGL 151 3

ACE 2. COMM 109 or COMM 209 or COMM 210 or COMM 286 or ALEC 102 3

ACE 3. STAT 218 or EDPS 459 3

ACE 4. *see course(s) listed in specific emphasis below 4

ACE 5. 3

ACE 6. CYAF 160 or EDPS 250 or EDPS 251 3

ACE 7. 3

ACE 8. SLPA 421 (if in Audiology or Speech-Pathology emphasis) or SLpA 490: Research Issues (if in Speech, Language, & Hearing Research Emphasis) 3

ACE 9. **see course(s) listed in specific emphasis below 3

ACE 10. See SLPA 496 in emphasis below fro total # of credit hours 3-12

Communication Sciences and Disorders Core Requirements 41 credits

GERO 200 or 455 or 459, SLPA 250, SLPA 453, SLPA 454 (3 credits); AGRO 315 OR BIOS 206, PSYC 181, SLPA 150, SLPA 251, SLPA 455, SLPA 456 (4 credits); MATH 103 OR 106 OR 106B (5 credits)

Choose one of the following Emphasis:

Audiology Emphasis 39 credits

SLPA 472, SLPA 473, SLPA 488** (3 credits each); BIOS 213/213L; CHEM 109 or higher*, LIFE 120/120L*, LIFE 121/121L*, PHYS 141 or higher*, SLPA 101, SLPA 102, SLPA 271 (4 credits each); BIOS 214 (5 credits); SLPA 496 (3-12 credits)

Speech, Language, & Hearing Research Emphasis 36-37 credits

BSEN 100 (1 credit), BSEN 112 (2 credits), BIOS 302, SLPA 490: Research Rotation & Reflection (3 credits each); BIOS 213/213L, CHEM 109 or higher*, LIFE 120/120L*, LIFE 121/121L*, PHYS 141 or higher* (4 credits each); CSCE 100, 101/101L, or 155 (3-4 credits); BIOS 214 (5 credits); SLPA 496 (6-12 credits)

Speech-Language Pathology 35-36 credits

EDPS 362 or 457, SLPA 441, SLPA 472, SLPA 488**, TEAC 259; TEAC 331, 430, 431, 434, OR 437 (3 credits each); any BIOS or LIFE course*, CHEM 109 or higher* OR PHYS 141 or higher*, SLPA 271, SLPA 461/461L, SLPA 464 (4 credits each); BIOS 213/213L OR BIOS 214 (4-5 credits); SLPA 496 (3-12 credits)

Electives 0-14

Total Hours 120

NOTE: SLPA students who complete sufficient course work in education will receive a minor in education along with the major degree.

ACE Requirements

All UNL students will be required to complete a minimum of 3 hours of approved course work in each of the 10 designated Achievement Centered Education (ACE) student learning outcome areas. These can be viewed at http://ace.unl.edu. Students will be provided a list of classes they can select from to meet each of the 10 ACE Student Learning Outcomes (SLO). There may be required courses within an education endorsement program that will also satisfy ACE requirements. Therefore, it is highly recommended that students contact their advisor prior to registering for ACE classes in order to insure that each of the class selections are in the best interest of the students’ academic program.

ADDITIONAL MAJOR/ENDORSEMENT REQUIREMENTS

Grade Requirements in Education Programs

Requirements for completion of an undergraduate degree in a teacher preparation program include a minimum cumulative grade point average (GPA) of 2.75. Students seeking certification must also have a 2.5 GPA in their endorsement and education courses with no grade lower than a C in their pre-professional courses and no grade lower than a C+ in their professional education courses.

Transfer Grades

Up to 9 hours of transfer credit with grades below C may be applied to the General Education requirements and elective classes in programs leading to the undergraduate degree in teacher preparation. Transfer grades of C- and D may not be used in the major/endorsement area courses or in the professional courses in teacher preparation programs.

Pass/No Pass Grade Option–for Education Students

A student enrolled at the University may, in certain instances, take a grading option of Pass/No Pass (P/N) for a specific course. A grade of pass represents satisfactory completion of a course with a grade of C or better. Credits earned under the pass grade option count toward graduation, but no grade points are tabulated in the cumulative grade point average. Likewise, a grade of No Pass is not tabulated in the grade point average. The following rules apply to students who are enrolled in teacher preparation programs who choose the Pass/No Pass option:

1. Only one course in each subject endorsement may be taken P/N; two courses in a field endorsement may be taken P/N.

2. Pre-professional and professional education classes may not be taken P/N unless a class already has a P/N designation.

3. Any course in the general education requirements unless otherwise stipulated by the department of the course may be taken P/N.

4. Total P/N credits may not exceed 12 credit hours. This limit does not include courses offered on a P/N only basis.

Students who are admitted through the Admission by Review process with core course deficiencies will have certain conditions attached to their enrollment at UNL.

Beyond Classroom Grades

In all fields of study, students are expected to attain certain grades and other academic accomplishments in the classroom. In addition to this, students preparing themselves to be teachers, counselors and for other careers in education, are also reviewed to evaluate their ability to successfully and safely interact with children, parents, potential educational employers, and the community-at-large, whose interest in the education of its children often exceeds its concern for other community and governmental services.

OTHER

Education Employment Services

The Career Services Center, 230 Nebraska Union, offers a professional placement service to students and alumni who are seeking employment in education and related fields. In addition to providing on-campus interviews with select schools throughout the year, this office sponsors an annual Education Recruitment Day in the spring, which offers students an opportunity to interview with hiring officials from many schools.

Criminal History Background Check Requirement

The College of Education and Human Sciences (CEHS) has the responsibility to ensure that all students who interact with children of all ages, served by schools or other public or private agencies meet a high level of personal, professional and ethical behavior. These CEHS students must complete an official criminal history background check through the CEHS vendor, prior to participating in a field experience or internship. Students are responsible for the cost of any required criminal history background check and will be required to complete one upon admission to a program and/or an initial field placement. Eighteen months after the initial background check has been completed, undergraduate students are required to complete the CEHS self-disclosure report, a self-report collected by the college. Graduate students will be required to complete the self-disclosure report at the same time as the initial background check is conducted and again eighteen months later. If more than three years have elapsed after the initial background check is conduced, CEHS students must complete an additional background check prior to participating in a field experience or internship. Students are responsible for the cost of additional background checks.

Students with felony or any misdemeanor charges or convictions, as reported on the background check, may be contacted by the College. Depending upon the frequency and severity of the charges and/or convictions, students may be required to meet with the Director of Professional Experiences. If any new charges or convictions are acquired after a background check has been completed, students are required to report those to the Director of Professional Experiences within two weeks after the event occurs. Failure to disclose any new information concerning one's criminal history can lead to removal from the program. Continued participation in school or community field experiences in the College will be based on the type and number of convictions, the recency of those occurrences, and whether they violate the requirements of the Nebraska Department of Education and/or the Nebraska Department of Health and Human Services. If the convictions are deemed to be serious in nature, a student may be prohibited from participating in a field experience in a pre-school, school or public agency setting. The student may then be referred to the department chair for further disciplinary action.

Professional and Ethical Behavior: Avoiding Risky Behaviors

Students planning to enter professions in education or the human sciences must be able to demonstrate that they are individuals of strong moral character who can make mature decisions for themselves and others. Therefore, the College of Education and Human Sciences requires that its students show a high degree of moral character and the ability to act in a responsible manner. Students must consider how the College, the profession, an employer, or the community perceive or evaluate the impact of any questionable behavior. Students' success in their profession is impaired by taking risks that are unacceptable for children, demonstrating a lack of professionalism and good judgment, and showing disregard for one's personal reputation or the integrity of the College.

The College of Education and Human Sciences reserves the right to evaluate student fitness for the profession and deny entry to or dismiss a student from any program if, through the reasonable exercise of the judgment of its Certification Officer or the Director of Professional Experiences, the College determines that the student's behavior represents a lack of integrity, questionable moral/ethical character, or represents risk to young persons. Such behaviors shall be adequate foundation to deny the student's participation in any practicum or field experience to protect the interests and safety of children. The consequences of unprofessional, unethical or risky behavior will depend upon the unique circumstances involved.

Appeal to the Dean

Should a student object to the determination made by the Certification Officer or the Director of Professional Experiences with respect to a criminal behavior or unprofessional behavior, the student may appeal to the Dean of the College, in writing, within ten days of the determination, requesting the Dean of the College to investigate and review the determination. The student's written appeal shall clearly explain the basis for the appeal. The Dean will review the student's basis for appeal and is authorized but not required to look into related concerns, whether or not sure concerns are contained in the student's written appeal. The Dean shall render a decision on the appeal as soon as reasonably possible, but in no case longer than 20 days following the initiation of the appeal. Once the Dean has completed the review and investigation, he or she shall deliver to the student and the Certification Officer or the Director of Professional Experiences a written decision, which shall be final and not subject to further appeal or review with the University of Nebraska.

Supply Chain Management

COLLEGE: Business Administration

MAJOR: Supply Chain Management

DEGREE OFFERED: Bachelor of Science in Business Administration

HOURS REQUIRED: 120 hours for degree (33 hours for the major)

MINIMUM CUMULATIVE GPA: 2.5 for graduation

MINOR AVAILABLE: Yes

ADVISOR: Jennifer Ryan, Scott R. Swenseth

DESCRIPTION

Chair: Jennifer Ryan

Professors: Olson, Schniederjans

Associate Professors: Swenseth, Trimi

Assistant Professors: Araz, Batur, Chen

Assistant Professor of Practice: Nabavi

The College of Business Administration at the University of Nebraska–Lincoln has established an undergraduate supply chain management major to educate students to become supply chain management professionals. Supply chain management (SCM) includes all the activities that must take place to get the right products and services into the right customer’s hands in the right quantity at the right time—from raw material extraction to consumer purchase.

The topics that SCM covers are diverse and include: procurement, order fulfillment, inventory management, supplier relationship management, product development and commercialization, returns management, physical distribution and shipping, warehousing, and outsourcing. With the depth and breadth of issues that it encompasses, industries that use SCM tools and approaches include: transportation, hospitals, government organizations, construction, processing, social services, electronics, facility design, manufacturing, and warehousing.

The course work for the supply chain management major (bachelor of science in business administration) consists of 120 credit hours, 33 of which are specific to the major. A focus of the course work is developing the three foundational areas of supply chain management: procurement, logistics, and operations. The program offers integration among these critical, value-adding components to enhance global competitiveness. Twenty-one hours of required course work is intended to provide students with an understanding of supply chain and logistic activities, development of strong quantitative and analytic skills, and introduction to tools to explore and improve a system. Students will complete an additional 12 hours of course work from directed electives in supporting fields such as accounting, economics, finance, management, or marketing.

ADMISSION

Admission requirements for all majors in the College are the same as those for University admission as noted under UNL General Admission Requirements.

MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Core Requirements

In addition to the College Degree Requirements, students will complete 33 hours of course work for the major.

All students, regardless of their major or interests in the College will take SCMS 331 and SCMS 350 as part of the Business Core Foundation requirements.

NONE of these courses may be used to count toward the major.

As noted in the College Degree Requirements section, all course work for the major must be taken for a grade.

Specific Major Requirements

Business Core Advanced–Major (BCA-M)

All course work for the major must be taken for a grade—no Pass/No Pass.

The requirements for the major in addition to the general College requirements, consists of 21 hours of required major courses as listed:

SCMA 335 Supply Chain Decision Making Models

MRKT 346 Marketing Channels Management (SCMS 346)

SCMA 431 Enterprise Management Systems

SCMA 432 Supply Chain Planning & Control Systems

MRKT 444 Supply Chain Logistics Management (SCMS 444)

SCMA 439 Global Sourcing & Distribution

SCMA 474 Strategic Supply Chain Management

As well as 12 hours from the following directed electives:

ACCT 301 Using Accounting Information

ACCT 308 Managerial Accounting

ACCT 309 Accounting Systems

ECON 321 Introduction to International Economics*

ECON 421 International Trade*

ECON 422 International Finance*

FINA 375 Financial Statement Analysis

MNGT 412 Negotiating and Conflict Management

MRKT 345 Marketing Research

MRKT 425 Retailing Management

SCMA 437 Supply Chain Risk Management

SCMA 454 Information Systems Analysis & Design

SCMA 458 Electronic Business

SCMA 459 Global Information Systems

SCMA 434 Lean Supply Chain Operations

SCMA 436 Project Management

SCMA 447 Supply Chain Technology

SCMA 451 Introduction to Predictive Analytics

SCMA 452 Database Organization & Management

* = No more than one ECON elective can be used to satisfy the SCMA elective requirements

ADDITIONAL MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Grade Rules

C- and D Grades

Same as College Grade rules.

Pass/No Pass Limits

Same as College Pass/No Pass limits.

GPA Requirements

Same as College GPA requirements.

REQUIREMENTS FOR MINOR OFFERED BY DEPARTMENT

Minor requirement is 12 hours of SCMS courses listed as core requirements or directed electives.

OTHER

Supply Chain Management Major

All course work for the major must be taken for a grade—no Pass/No Pass. Course work applied to the SCMS major cannot be used towards the completion of any other major or minor in the college.